Big Joe Turner Papers ARC.0105
Library and Archives
Big Joe Turner Papers
Bulk, 1976-1986
1945-1986
ARC.0105
Library and Archives
1.0 Linear feet One records carton
The Big Joe Turner Papers highlight the latter part of Turner's sixty-year career as a pioneering and influential blues singer. The collection dates from 1945 to 1986, with the bulk of the material focusing on the period from 1976 to 1986. Materials include documents, correspondence, printed materials, telegrams, certificates of recognition, blues festival programs, photographs, and negatives. The collection features Turner's 1984 and 1985 Grammy Award nomination cards and corresponding information regarding the events, documentation surrounding Turners's search for his birth certificate, and correspondence from notable figures, such as Jann Wenner, Ahmet Ertegun, Dick Clark, and Doc Pomus. The Big Joe Turner Papers include information regarding the benefit concert Joe's wife, Pat, and his friends were organizing to help pay for the artist's skyrocketing medical bills. Turner passed away two weeks before the scheduled show in 1985. The collection contains two guestbooks from his funeral, as well as letters of condolence to Pat acknowledging her husband's significant contributions to the music world and the history of rock and roll.
Biographical Note
1911 May 18 Born Joseph Vernon Turner, Jr. in Kansas City, Missouri
1938 December 23 Appears at "Spirituals to Swing" concert at Carnegie Hall in New York City
1939 Releases first single, "Roll 'em Pete," with boogie woogie pianist Pete Johnson With Albert Ammons and Meade Lux Lewis, begins a five-year residency at New York's Cafe Society
1946 August 3 "My Gal's a Jockey" becomes Turner's first single to make the Billboard R&B chart
1954 May 8 "Shake, Rattle and Roll" enters the Billboard charts, peaks at #1 on the R&B charts, and #2 on the Pop charts
1956 Appears in the film Shake, Rattle and Roll
1983 Album Blues Train is released Inducted into the Blues Hall of Fame
1985 November 24 Dies in Inglewood, California
1987 January 21 Posthumously inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame
Big Joe Turner was among the first to mix R&B with boogie-woogie, resulting in jump blues, a style that presaged the birth of rock and roll. Turner’s original recording of “Shake, Rattle and Roll,” cut for Atlantic Records in 1954, remains one of the cornerstones of the rock and roll revolution. Turner’s lengthy career touched on most developments in popular music, taking him from the big bands of the Swing Era to boogie-woogie, rhythm & blues, and rock and roll. Turner recorded prolifically in the Forties for various labels, including Decca, National, and Aladdin. He worked with Pete Johnson as well as a number of other pianists, including such giants as Albert Ammons, Willie “the Lion” Smith, and Meade Lux Lewis. In 1946, Turner had his first R&B hit, “My Gal’s a Jockey,” released on Herb Abramson’s National label. Abramson would go on to cofound Atlantic Records with Ahmet Ertegun 1948. In 1951, Ertegun brought Turner to Atlantic Records, where he cut a string of rhythm & blues and early rock and roll classics over the next decade; among them were “Chains of Love,” “Sweet Sixteen,” “Honey Hush,” Shake, Rattle and Roll,” “Flip Flop and Fly,” and “Corrine Corinna.” Pianist Fats Domino accompanied Turner on the romping “TV Mama.” “Shake, Rattle and Roll” and “Honey Hush” topped the R&B charts for three and eight weeks, respectively.
In the Sixties, after the first wave of rock and roll had died down, Turner returned to blues and boogie-woogie. He moved to Los Angeles, where he recorded with jazz legends like Dizzy Gillespie, Count Basie, and Roy Eldridge for some well-received albums on the Pablo label. The 1983 album Blues Train, on which he was backed by Roomful of Blues and produced by Doc Pomus, was a late-career success. Having outlasting trends until his sound had became timeless, Big Joe Turner continued to record and perform until his death in 1985.
Sources
"Big Joe Turner Biography." Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum. Accessed May 26, 2011. http://rockhall.com/inductees/big-joe-turner/bio/.
Scope and Contents
The Big Joe Turner Papers span the years 1945-1986. The papers are arranged by series and then alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Provacy Rights form before using this collection. Please contact staff before visiting the Library and Archives to use this collection.
Separated Materials
Periodicals have been transferred to the library collection. Search "Big Joe Turner Papers" in the library catalog for a complete list of titles.
Provenance
The Big Joe Turner Papers were recieved by The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Inc. as a gift from Pat Turner in 1994.
Atlantic Recording Corporation; Turner, Joe, 1911-1985; Blues (Music).; Blues-rock music.; Boogie woogie (Music); Correspondence.; Doo-Wop (Music); Guitar music (Rock); Legal documents--Music trade.; Musicians--United States--Biography.; Photographs.; Popular music--United States.; Rhythm and blues music.; Singers--United States--Biography.
- Series I: Awards and Certificates, 1976-1986
  - Awards and certificates, 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Museum Accession Numbers
    A1994.4.10-A1994.4.22
  - Grammy awards nomination and information, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    A1994.4.90-A1994.4.91
- Series II: Business Files, 1945-1946, 1983-1984, and undated
  - Business papers, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    A1994.4.77-A1994.4.83
  - California Afro-American Museum artifact control sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyers, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    A1994.4.84-A1994.4.85, A1994.4.94
  - Printed lyrics, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Musuem Accession Numbers
    A1994.4.23a-A1994.4.23j, A1994.4.24a-A1994.4.24b, A1994.25a-A1994.25j
- Series III: Correspondence, 1942-1987
  - Letters, 1942-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    A1994.4.26-A.1994.4.58, A1994.4.74-A1994.4.76
  - Telegrams, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    A1994.4.88a-A1994.4.88e, A1994.4.89a-A.1994.4.89c
- Series IV: Memorial Files, 1985-1986
  - Big Joe Turner memorial service, "Friends Who Called" book from Angelus Funeral Home, circa 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    A1994.4.1a-A1994.4.1b
  - Memorial and benefit concerts, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    A1994.4.2-A1994.4.8
- Series V: Personal Files, 1971-1977 and undated
  - Biographical information, 1976-1977 and undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    A1994.4.9, A1994.4.86-A1994.4.87
  - Passport information, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    A1994.4.60-A1994.4.64
  - Work permit, 1974 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    A1994.4.65
- Series VI: Photographic Materials, undated
  - Negatives and transparencies, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    A1994.4.66-A1994.4.1972
  - Black and white publicity photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    A1994.4.73
- Series VII: Printed Materials
  - Clippings, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pamphlets, 1974 and 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)